<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-09-27T18:43:10-05:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Jay Gaura</title><subtitle>&quot;Sharing insights on personal growth, community, and tech innovation. Join me in contributing to a more harmonious world through self-improvement.&quot; — Jay Gaura (Visnujan das)</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Fate vs Free Will!</title><link href="/2024/09/fate-vs-free-will.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fate vs Free Will!" /><published>2024-09-26T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-09-26T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/2024/09/fate-vs-free-will</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/09/fate-vs-free-will.html"><![CDATA[<p><strong>Fate and Free Will: A VR Game Analogy</strong></p>

<p><em>Once in a while, I post answers on Quora, and here’s my take on this topic:</em></p>

<div class="post-img"><img src="/assets/img/2024/free-will.jpg" alt="Fate vs Free Will!" /></div>

<p>I hope you’ve had some experience with VR games or any computer games, because I’m going to use a VR analogy to explain.</p>

<p>When you put on a VR headset, you’re exercising your free will. However, once you’re in the game, you’re fully subject to the logic and rules created by the game developers. You think you’re making choices—hitting a ball, scoring points—but in reality, you’re just operating within the boundaries of the game’s design. To someone watching from the outside, your actions might even look strange or amusing.</p>

<p>Now, if you don’t get too carried away, you can always take the headset off—that’s your free will again.</p>

<p>This analogy works when discussing fate and free will in a spiritual context. God desires a genuine relationship with us, which can only exist if both parties are free. No one wants a relationship based solely on dependency or ulterior motives. For that reason, God grants us free will—the freedom to choose or reject a relationship with Him. Just like in this game you’re free to buy and use your games.</p>

<p>The problem is, in the absolute reality, there’s nothing but God—everything is part of Him, His energies, His creation. Put another way, God is too good to be rejected. By definition, God is the perfection, the absolute best at everything… To allow for true freedom, a world had to be created where God isn’t an obvious, overwhelming presence. In this “game”, God is optional, a matter of belief. This is the material world, which represents the VR game in this analogy, the virtual reality where God is optional and belief in Him is a matter of choice. It’s an artificial environment, a “fake” world in that it covers up the real reality. Now, how can we truly be free in a fake reality where we don’t belong, and were all we interact with is made up? That’s why, despite how compelling this “reality” seems (and no one wants to leave it), it remains unfulfilling.</p>

<p>Just like in the VR game, we have the free will to take off the headset and return to reality, but we often get caught up in the illusion.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="world" /><category term="bhakti" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Quora question: How do you explain fate and free will?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Making Tech Work Smarter for You</title><link href="/2024/09/making-tech-work-smarter-for-you.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Making Tech Work Smarter for You" /><published>2024-09-25T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-09-25T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/2024/09/making-tech-work-smarter-for-you</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/09/making-tech-work-smarter-for-you.html"><![CDATA[<div class="post-img"><img src="/assets/img/2024/tech3.jpg" alt="Making Tech Work Smarter for You" /></div>

<p>I’ve been a self-taught programmer for over 20 years, working on everything from solo gigs to large corporate projects. One thing that’s consistently stood out: things often could be done better—more efficiently, more cost-effectively. I’ve seen projects that could’ve saved hundreds of hours with just a bit more planning upfront.</p>

<p>Technology moves so fast that it’s hard to keep up with “what’s now possible.” New tools, methods, and systems constantly emerge, and it’s easy to miss out on advancements while keeping up with the day-to-day. This often leads to sticking with outdated processes that still “work well enough” but could be costing time and money.</p>

<p>That’s where I come in. I focus on automating processes—“making computers work hard for humans.” My goal is to help businesses unlock what’s possible today and avoid wasting resources on inefficient old approaches.</p>

<p>I love solving problems and finding elegant, efficient solutions. It’s frustrating to come into a project when it’s too late to fix things properly, which is why I’d rather be there from the start. Give me a challenge, and I’ll tackle it with creativity and experience, all while keeping communication clear so you’re confident about the project’s direction.</p>

<p>At the core of it all, I love what I do, and I’m always looking for ways to do it better.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="business" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Automating processes to save time, money, and streamline business]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Proof is in the Garage Sale</title><link href="/2024/08/the-proof-is-in-the-garage-sale.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Proof is in the Garage Sale" /><published>2024-08-13T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2024-08-13T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/2024/08/the-proof-is-in-the-garage-sale</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2024/08/the-proof-is-in-the-garage-sale.html"><![CDATA[<div class="post-img"><img src="/assets/img/2024/garage-sale2.jpg" alt="The Proof is in the Garage Sale" /></div>

<p>We, humans, are driven by deep desires, but what we truly seek is personal fulfillment, not just the fleeting satisfaction of our wants. How do we know this? Take a look at the American tradition of “garage sales”—a sale of items we once craved, yet no longer need or care for. It’s proof that mere desire fulfillment isn’t the endgame; it’s a temporary stop on the journey toward real, lasting happiness.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="world" /><category term="bhakti" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Desires come and go, but real happiness is what we seek. How do we know?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Vessels of Divine Love</title><link href="/2023/02/vessels-of-divine-love.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Vessels of Divine Love" /><published>2023-02-16T00:00:00-06:00</published><updated>2023-02-16T00:00:00-06:00</updated><id>/2023/02/vessels-of-divine-love</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2023/02/vessels-of-divine-love.html"><![CDATA[<div class="slider-container"><div class="slide fade">
                            <div class="numbertext">1 / 2</div>
                            <img src="/assets/img/vaisnavas/dear/bv-tirtha.jpg" style="width:100%" />
                          </div><div class="slide fade">
                            <div class="numbertext">2 / 2</div>
                            <img src="/assets/img/vaisnavas/dear/uma-didi.jpg" style="width:100%" />
                          </div><a class="prev" onclick="plusSlides(-1)">&#10094;</a><a class="next" onclick="plusSlides(1)">&#10095;</a></div>
<div class="slider-navigation"><span class="dot" onclick="currentSlide(1)"></span><span class="dot" onclick="currentSlide(2)"></span></div>
<script>
          let slideIndex = 1;
          showSlides(slideIndex);
  
          function plusSlides(n) {
            showSlides(slideIndex += n);
          }
  
          function currentSlide(n) {
            showSlides(slideIndex = n);
          }
  
          function showSlides(n) {
            let i;
            let slides = document.getElementsByClassName('slide');
            let dots = document.getElementsByClassName('dot');
            if (n > slides.length) { slideIndex = 1; }
            if (n < 1) { slideIndex = slides.length; }
            for (i = 0; i < slides.length; i++) {
              slides[i].style.display = 'none';
            }
            for (i = 0; i < dots.length; i++) {
              dots[i].className = dots[i].className.replace(' active', '');
            }
            slides[slideIndex - 1].style.display = 'block';
            dots[slideIndex - 1].className += ' active';
          }
        </script>

<p>I lost two very special and dear friends over the last couple of years. One very recently. They were Vaishnavas, devotees of God, devotees of Krishna. Vaishnavas exemplify everything I’ve tried to convey here so far, and much more. Krishna, God, is an ocean of love and divine qualities. Vaishnavas worship Him, immersing themselves in that ocean, saturating their hearts with divine love. By doing this, they achieve true happiness and fulfillment, becoming sources of love and affection themselves. It’s like a cup overflowing—when you’re full, you naturally spill over, sharing your love.</p>

<p>That’s the secret to being truly loving and happy: connecting to the source of love, God Himself. Vaishnavas represent what humanity could be at its best. Imagine a world where people were fulfilled within, overflowing with love, care, and support. Everyone wants to give, uplift, and support, rather than take, manipulate, or put others down. God’s limitless kindness manifests in countless ways, but in Vaishnavas, it expresses itself in a unique, personal way. In different cultures, these devotees are called by various names—saints, sadhus, fakirs—but their essence remains the same.</p>

<p>The two Vaishnavas I lost were Sripad Bhaktivedanta Tirtha Maharaja and Srimati Uma Didi. I had the good fortune to meet them and serve them in small ways, such as driving them during their travels and assisting with their preaching. These experiences gave me a glimpse, even if limited, into how wonderful and sweet the nature of Vaishnavas truly is. Just remembering them now brings me both great joy and deep sorrow.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="bhakti" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A tribute to two great Vaisnava friends I lost]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Happiness: The Missing Variable</title><link href="/2022/04/happiness-the-missing-variable.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Happiness: The Missing Variable" /><published>2022-04-04T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2022-04-04T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>/2022/04/happiness-the-missing-variable</id><content type="html" xml:base="/2022/04/happiness-the-missing-variable.html"><![CDATA[<div class="post-img"><img src="/assets/img/2024/missing-variable3.jpg" alt="Happiness: The Missing Variable" /></div>

<h3 id="common-ground-as-a-basis-for-discussion">Common Ground as a Basis for Discussion</h3>

<p>We humans naturally develop worldviews and opinions, which often lead us into discussions—or even debates. In any meaningful exchange of ideas, establishing clear common ground becomes crucial—a foundation that all parties can agree on. But what exactly is this common ground if we consider a global or objective truth? I have my own thoughts on the matter, which I’ll share below for you to reflect on. Let’s see if we can find agreement or consensus, or perhaps even spark a discussion.</p>

<p>We also need a shared way to measure progress. Without a mutual understanding of what progress looks like, how can we decide if we’re heading in the right direction? For some, the release of the latest iPhone represents a clear milestone in human advancement. Others might argue that such technology makes us more distracted, less connected to the world around us.</p>

<p>My hope is that the “common ground” I mentioned earlier can also serve as a shared framework for evaluating progress. Below, I’ll outline my own view—let’s see where we stand.</p>

<h3 id="seekers-of-joy-and-fulfillment">Seekers of Joy and Fulfillment</h3>

<p>One fundamental truth, which I believe we can all agree on, is that human beings are driven by an unyielding desire for joy and happiness. This impulse guides everything we do, shaping our choices and our actions. When someone makes a sacrifice, whether for family, community, or country, it’s motivated by love. And the remarkable thing about love is that it brings joy, even in sacrifice—because love, at its core, is rewarding. Artists create because they love expressing their innermost emotions, scientists work tirelessly out of passion and faith, all in pursuit of fulfillment and happiness. Even wrongful acts, at their root, stem from a misguided belief that they will bring pleasure or gain. We may disagree on the method, but the aim is universal: to experience joy.</p>

<p>The Bible tells us that man is made in God’s image, and many spiritual traditions, including Gaudiya Vaishnavism, describe God as the ultimate enjoyer. In this specific tradition, God—Krishna—is portrayed as the supreme lover, engaged in eternal pastimes filled with divine joy and love. Other religions also emphasize God’s love, mercy, and kindness, closely linked to the idea of joy and fulfillment.</p>

<p>If God is the supreme enjoyer and the ultimate beloved, what does that make us, being created in His image? It makes us seekers—driven by the desire for joy and pleasure, though on a much smaller scale. God, however, has already found eternal fulfillment and exists in perfect harmony and love. In contrast, we are still on the journey, often seeking happiness in temporary or material things. This pursuit can sometimes lead us astray.</p>

<p>Love is the key to true joy, and finding the love of God is the pinnacle of this search. While love in this world—such as love for children—is powerful, it is often transactional and rooted in the workings of nature. Parents love and protect their children, and later in life, they hope to receive love, support, and appreciation in return. Divine love, on the other hand, is unchanging and causeless. God’s love transcends time, space, and even life itself.</p>

<p>This is why the love of God is considered the highest form of love, the ultimate fulfillment. While the material world keeps us restless and searching, divine love brings an end to that quest. It offers a peace and contentment that surpasses all worldly experiences. The search ends, and peace follows.</p>

<h3 id="progress-measurement">Progress Measurement</h3>

<p>So, how do we measure progress? If happiness is the goal, we need to assess how much happier and fulfilled we’ve become. As the soul becomes more content, the desire for external things—along with the tension from competing for resources—should diminish. If you’re already fulfilled, what more is there to chase?</p>

<p>The wars, political struggles, and relentless competition we see around us indicate that both individuals and society are far from fulfilled. We sense this lack, and although we haven’t found true happiness, our frantic search continues—often in destructive ways. Instead of rushing headlong into conflict and chaos, maybe it’s time to pause, reassess, and think beyond the usual methods. If happiness and fulfillment are truly our goals, why do we so often contribute to war and discord? Are these really paths to happiness, or are they steering us toward self-destruction?</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="world" /><category term="bhakti" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Explore the key to lasting joy and inner peace.]]></summary></entry></feed>